Payton E. Rodman

Institute of Astronomy, University of Cambridge, Madingley Rd, Cambridge CB3 0HA www.paytonelyce.com

Summary of Research Interests

My current research focuses on the inflow and outflow of material from around supermassive black holes such as those found in the centres of massive galaxies. My thesis aims to investigate how magnetic fields may impact the evolution of both accretion disks and relativistic jets, through the use of the magnetohydrodynamics (MHD) codes Athena++ and PLUTO.

Education

PhD Astronomy Cambridge, UK 2019 - 2024

University of Cambridge, Institute of Astronomy / Churchill College

Thesis: TBA

Supervisor: Professor Christopher Reynolds

Hobart, AUS **BSc (Hons) Physics**

University of Tasmania 2018

Thesis: Probing Intracluster Gas with Faraday Rotation from Black Hole Jets

Supervisors: Dr Stanislav Shabala, Dr Ross Turner

BSc Physics and Applied Mathematics

Hobart, AUS University of Tasmania 2015 - 2017

Publications

- 1. Faraday rotation as a probe of radio galaxy environment in RMHD AGN jet simulations Jerrim, L. A., Shabala, S. S., Yates-Jones, P. M., Krause, M. G. H., Turner, R. J., Anderson, C. S., Stewart, G. S. C., Power, C., Rodman, P. E. (2023), submitted to MNRAS
- 2. Evolution of the Magnetic Field in High- and Low-β Disks with Initially Toroidal Fields Rodman, P. E., Reynolds, C. S. (2024), ApJ, 960:97
- 3. How do magnetic field models affect astrophysical limits on light axion-like particles? An X-ray case study with NGC 1275 Matthews, J. H., Reynolds, C. S., Marsh, M. C. D., Sisk-Reynés, J., Rodman, P. E. (2022), ApJ, 930:90
- 4. Radio Galaxy Zoo: observational evidence for environment as the cause of radio source asymmetry Rodman, P. E., Turner, R. J., Shabala, S. S., Banfield, J. K., Wong, O.-I., Andernach, H., Garon, A. F., Kapińska, A. D., Norris, R. P., Rudnick, L. (2019), MNRAS, 482(4):5625-5641

Invited and Contributed Talks

Nov 2022: University of Bremen, Invited talk

Sep 2022: 31st Symposium on Relativistic Astrophysics, Prague, Contributed talk

Teaching

Lent 2020: Supervisions for Astrophysical Fluid Dynamics in Part II

Sem 2 2019 Marker for Statistical Physics and Solid State Physics

Sem 1 2018, 2019 Marker for Physics 1A

Sem 2 2018 Marker for Physics 1B

Skills

- Programming / scripting languages: C++, Python, MATLAB, LATEX, Mathematica
- Simulation codes: Athena++, Рьито
- Languages: English (native), French (A2)

Previous Research Experience

Undergraduate Vacation Scholar

Perth, AUS

CSIRO Astronomy and Space Science

Nov 2016 - Feb 2017

Supervisor: Dr Cormac Reynolds

Used large-scale, multi-epoch surveys to study variability in radio sources caused by inhomogeneities in the interstellar and intergalactic medium.

Summer Research Student

Hobart, AUS

University of Tasmania

Nov 2015 - Feb 2016

Supervisors: Dr Stanislav Shabala, Dr Ross Turner

Used data from the citizen science project *Radio Galaxy Zoo* to study whether nearby galaxy clustering affects the physical properties of AGN jets, with focus on classical double radio galaxies. A paper detailing the findings has been published in MNRAS.

Awards and Scholarships

- 2019: Gates-Cambridge Scholarship
- 2018: Dean's Honour Roll for Bachelor of Science with Honours
- 2018: Ken McCracken Prize for the best Honours thesis in the discipline of Physics
- 2018: Vice-Chancellor's Leadership Award
- 2018: Don Gaffney Scholarship
- 2017: AIP Summer Meeting Travel Scholarship
- 2017: Dean's Honour Roll for Bachelor of Science
- 2017: Australian Institute of Physics Prize for the greatest proficiency in third-year Physics
- 2017: TEMCO Community Foundation Scholarship in Science
- 2016: Sir Phillip Fysh Prize for the best student in second-year Physics
- 2016: CSIRO Undergraduate Vacation Scholarship
- 2015: Dean's Summer Research Scholarship
- 2015: John Fox Memorial Prize for the best female student in first-year Physics and Mathematics
- 2015: F.M. Young Memorial Prize for the greatest proficiency in first-year Bachelor of Science
- 2015: Dean's Summer Research Scholarship
- 2015: Dr. Peter Smith Scholarship in the Physical Sciences

Public Outreach

2017–2019: Tastrofest (1hr), invited public lectures on black holes

2016–2019: University of Tasmania Open Days and Cub Scout Visits, regular volunteer

2019: Tasmanian Youth Science Forum Panellist

2018: UTAS Science & Engineering Investigation Awards Head Judge

2018: BeakerStreet@TMAG Roving Scientist

2018: Festival of Bright Ideas Presenter

2018: Young Tassie Scientist